<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
     xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
     xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
     xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
  <channel>
    <title>Simple Blog</title>
    <atom:link
      href="http://sivark.me/blog/feed.xml"
      rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <link>http://sivark.me/blog/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
    <language>en</language>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 13:04:17 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>weblorg 0.1.0 (https://emacs.love/weblorg)</generator>
    <webMaster>web@master (Blog Author)</webMaster>
    <image>
      <url>http://sivark.me/blog/index.htmlmedia/img/8bitme.png</url>
      <title>Blog Author</title>
      <link>http://sivark.me/blog/index.html</link>
    </image>

    
    <item>
      <title>Ergodicity Economics and von Neumann-Morgenstern utility</title>
      <link>http://sivark.me/blog/ergodicity-economics-and-von-neumann-morgenstern-utility.html</link>
      <author>Siva Swaminathan</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://sivark.me/blog/ergodicity-economics-and-von-neumann-morgenstern-utility.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>
I have seen claims that the von Neumann Morgenstern utility theorem (vNM) grounding Expected Utility Theory (EUT) voids <a href="https://ergodicityeconomics.com/">Ergodicity Economics</a> (EE) and time averages, including appeals to authority about von Neumann being an expert on the idea of (non)ergodicity. I think that misses a subtlety. I have tried to avoid any use of "right" or "wrong", instead trying to emphasize the <i>"usefulness"</i> of modeling assumptions given the situation.
</p>

<p>
The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Von_Neumann%E2%80%93Morgenstern_utility_theorem">vNM theorem</a> guarantees the existence of a utility function IFF four axioms (termed {completeness, transitivity, continuity, independence}) are satisfied. Quite reasonable on the face of it, but the theorem implicitly assumes the existence of a probability distribution, and doesn't say anything about where the probabilities come from. That choice is a separate <b>modeling assumption</b> when applying the vNM framework to a specific situation.
</p>

<p>
Consider the simple experiment of repeated tosses of a fair coin, doubling or halving the agent's wealth on each turn<sup><a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="#fn.1">1</a></sup>. <i>What probability distribution over the set of trajectories is appropriate to capture the agent's behavior?</i> Note that vNM has nothing to say about this &#x2013; leaving it up to the modeler to choose judiciously. That choice implicitly decides between time and ensemble averages (or whatever else kind of average).
</p>

<p>
If we expect this game to be played a small number of times compared with the number of trajectories (eg: a billion = 2<sup>30</sup> &lt;&lt; 2<sup>100</sup>, for 100 sequential coin tosses), then the distribution of <i>"typical"</i> trajectories <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concentration_of_measure"><i>concentrates</i></a> around the median case (expected number of H and T) with probability approaching one, leaving the agent almost no chance to probe the extreme scenarios (long strings of H or long strings of T). This concentrated measure which describes how the (available "small" number of) agents/plays will "probe" the trajectories and leads to what we call "time averages"<sup><a id="fnr.2" class="footref" href="#fn.2">2</a></sup> is very different from the distribution corresponding to ensemble probabilities of trajectories, where each trajectory is equally likely (for a fair coin).
</p>

<p>
The only way to realize a situation which circumvents this concentration of measure is to live in the regime where the number of (parallel) plays far exceeds the number of trajectories. In such a scenario, it will turn out that the distribution probed by the ensemble of agents/plays corresponds to what we call the "ensemble average"<sup><a id="fnr.3" class="footref" href="#fn.3">3</a></sup> among the trajectories.
</p>

<p>
To be even more thorough, we care about the probability distribution not in the space of trajectories, but the induced distribution on the observable (i.e. the space of payoffs) &#x2013; which is the quantity we are actually averaging. These two distributions could look very different eg. in cases where a small set of trajectories in the ensemble have outsized (exponentially large) payoffs! IFF we happen to be in the latter situation (depending on the observable/payoff, and the process) we may call the {observable, process} combination  <i>"ergodic"</i>.
</p>

<div class="outline-2">
<h2 id="ergodicity-and-economic-modeling"><span class="section-number-2">1</span> Ergodicity and economic modeling</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
EE is not in opposition with the vNM framework! Rather, <i>the point of EE is that one can avoid performing complicated gymnastics with utilities/payoffs to model behavior, if one is instead more judicious about the probabilities multiplying them</i>. That is the role played by time averages instead of ensemble averages.
</p>

<p>
If one were only interested in modeling a single problem, the prescription of distribution is about as much input as a prescription of utilities &#x2013; they both beg the question equally, in a sense. The true value of EE comes from its potential <i>generalizability to modeling multiple problems with the same prescription of averaging</i> if it turns out that the prescription of time averages is sufficient to correctly model behaviour using simple/obvious utility functions, rather than cooking up a different utility function to model the behavior in each problem.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div class="outline-2">
<h2 id="ergodicity-and-physical-systems"><span class="section-number-2">2</span> Ergodicity and physical systems</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
<p>
We have all the pieces in place to understand the roots of ergodicity in physical systems, so we might as well touch on that. (This section is a digression from the economics discussion, and can be safely skipped by readers primarily interested in that.)
</p>

<p>
The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ergodic_hypothesis">ergodic hypothesis</a> claims that (even) a single agent (i.e. a physical system in a given macrostate) will (over a reasonable time scale) uniformly explore the microstates in the ensemble corresponding to the macrostate (through natural dynamics).
The only observables that can be probed by experiments on a single system (or a few systems) are time averages, but the ergodic hypothesis allows those to be equated with ensemble averages (which are far easier to compute). For this replacement to be a useful model (at least in non-pathological systems), we don't really need the system's trajectory to probe <i>all</i> the microstates, but merely to probe the phase space volume densely<sup><a id="fnr.4" class="footref" href="#fn.4">4</a></sup> and uniformly. Loosely speaking, chaotic dynamics can induce a dense sampling, while Liouville's theorem guarantees uniformity along the trajectory. There are caveats to that statement, whose subtleties I haven't fully mapped out yet; suffice to say that there are interesting examples where this doesn't trivially happen, such as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermi%E2%80%93Pasta%E2%80%93Ulam%E2%80%93Tsingou_problem">Fermi–Pasta–Ulam–Tsingou problem</a> or <a href="http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Glassy_dynamics">glassy dynamics</a>.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="footnotes">
<h2 class="footnotes">Footnotes: </h2>
<div id="text-footnotes">

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="#fnr.1">1</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">Somewhat like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Petersburg_paradox">St. Petersburg paradox</a>, but not quite.</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.2" class="footnum" href="#fnr.2">2</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">The concentrated measure is basically the model underlying the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelly_criterion">Kelly criterion</a>.</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.3" class="footnum" href="#fnr.3">3</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">This is the commonly (implicitly) assumed situation in probability theory &#x2013; where the number of trials (far) exceeds the number of events underlying a random variable (validating a frequentist perspective) &#x2013; under which ensemble averaging turns out to be a meaningful/useful concept, because of the concentration driven by the law of large numbers.</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.4" class="footnum" href="#fnr.4">4</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">Like the <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1027970/what-does-it-mean-for-rational-numbers-to-be-dense-in-the-reals">rationals among the reals</a>.</p></div></div>


</div>
</div>]]></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is art?</title>
      <link>http://sivark.me/blog/what-is-art.html</link>
      <author>Siva Swaminathan</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://sivark.me/blog/what-is-art.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>
Art is not about paints and canvas, or instruments, or words, or body movements. Those are merely mediums for expression. The essence of art is about <b>seeing</b> (sensing, perceiving) something that others might not, and communicating &amp; sharing that, through whichever medium might be conveniently expressive.
</p>

<p>
If the essence of art is sharing/communication, what is beauty? It is about the emotions it invokes in the receiver. Work that induces acute feelings (intentionally, not accidentally) could be appreciated as <b>beautiful</b> in the sense of effectively conveying a message.
</p>

<p>
Sometimes, the message might simply be the mastery of a medium or form (including the human physical form), in which case the "beauty" might associate more intrinsically with just the method &amp; its expression, rather than with some extrinsic content.
</p>

<p>
Typically, the most natural path for the emergence of a work of such beauty is a deep involvement between the person and the medium (the subject/person and the object/work), shaping each into a good fit for the other. It is worth noting that the deep involvement might be not directly in the output, but in the medium i.e. the doing of the work. At the same time, the doing has to be un-self-conscious.
</p>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Artifacts produced in this manner get called "art", though it's worth discriminating between the process and the artifacts. Art <span class="underline">works</span> are (imho) valueable not intrinsically, but for the message they carry &#x2013; especially for their potency in offering a new perspective of reality, in contrast to those embedded in a certain context and history. They might be so effective in reshaping the sensory experience that they automatically lead to a consequential change in behavior. Absorbed into the human experience, they forever change how we perceive things.<sup><a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="#fn.1">1</a></sup>
</p>

<p>
In this sense, the most beautiful composition would be meaningless (in the sense of not carrying a message) if it were generated "randomly" by a computer. The content of human value is not typically the artifact or the method, but the message it encodes, and the feeling it (intentionally) engenders in the receiver.
</p>

<p>
Essential to the practice of art is a give-and-take (art works and attention) between the artist and their audience. Technology might create new mediums with expressive freedoms, but if it also disintermediates the aboe relationship then it destroys the possibility of constructing art.
</p>

<p>
Art, in this sense, involves indirect communication, sharing perceptions that might not easily be conveyed by other means.
</p>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
It is often very hard to communicate ideas in abstract, and the best way to share is to actually reify the idea into something concrete &#x2013; using an apropos medium.
The medium may be chosen for a combination of its affordances, and your proficiency/skill in <b>playing</b> with it.
</p>

<p>
Sometimes the reification might be so subtle as to simply enable the creation of a mood/atmosphere for the listener to dwell in, which might invoke certain insights. I tend to use multiple media in this manner, especially books (for their intended message) &amp; music (often the mood they create is not the primary target, but simply in service of some other line of thought).
</p>

<p>
The expressive medium could be pretty much anything &#x2013; including engineering, economics, software, communities/organizations, etc, and ways of “playing” those media might involve anything from scientific research to starting a company to managing people &amp; organizations.<sup><a id="fnr.2" class="footref" href="#fn.2">2</a></sup>
</p>

<p>
In this perspective, media are merely vessels &#x2013; a means to communicate &#x2013; and come and go as the circumstances of technology and society evolve. It's worth keeping separate any specific medium from the deeper idea of perception &amp; communication.
</p>

<p>
Each medium distorts the message in its own manner, so much that one might often need to invent a new medium for a new thought/message. This is especially true with <span class="underline">language</span>, for its <span class="underline">affordances</span> (the concepts it affords; words/phrases) are like grooves/ruts of convenience, that tend to become patterns of thought.
</p>

<p>
We often wear several layers of tinted galsses when we see the world, and radically new forms of perception often involve removing one of those, to see the world better.
</p>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Every human activity, including life itself, is potentially a canvas on which you create art given your unique combination of constraints and freedom. This is a medium available to <b>everyone</b>, and it behooves us to indulge in this process in the spirit of <b>play</b> (the idea of `leela`). A life "well lived" may well be considered a work of art.
</p>

<p>
<b>Play</b> is just practicing <b>expressive freedom</b> through some medium or the other, by typically by reifying some message of choice.
</p>

<p>
The (main?) application of technology is, imho, to expand artistic freedom and agency &#x2013; to help people <span class="underline">get a grip</span> (affordances) on tools and media so they may express themselves artistically (including self-authoring).
</p>


<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
None of what I've said might come as a revelation to anyone who's devoted many years to art, but as someone who has not, and has never consciously reflected on this question till recently, I find that this to be a potent insight to play with.
</p>
<div id="footnotes">
<h2 class="footnotes">Footnotes: </h2>
<div id="text-footnotes">

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="#fnr.1">1</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">The art market is a strange beast. For all practical purposes, I consider a photograph or a copy of a painting almost as valuable as the original, especially when one has to work hard to prove a meaningful difference</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.2" class="footnum" href="#fnr.2">2</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">Teaching a kid painting is no different, in this sense, from teaching a kid programming</p></div></div>


</div>
</div>]]></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Great Rebalancing, by Michael Pettis</title>
      <link>http://sivark.me/blog/the-great-rebalancing-by-michael-pettis.html</link>
      <author>Siva Swaminathan</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://sivark.me/blog/the-great-rebalancing-by-michael-pettis.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>
(2013), so it is interesting to see how the book has aged.
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>The way I would phrase his punchline: <b>In a globalized world, all domestic policy is trade policy.</b></li>
<li>Makes the point (and cites consensus among economic historians) that imperialism was driven by finding a market for excess production ("savings") generated by the industrial revolution (Ref: Hobson, Luxemburg, Lenin)</li>
<li>\(\textrm{GDP} \equiv \textrm{Consumption} + \textrm{Surplus (invested productively or not)}\) (eg: Refers to production surplus as "savings" which is unusual; normal English usage would lead one to consider <i>uninvested &amp; fungible</i> capital as savings, not quite production in excess of consumption, but maybe the wording is not crucial for the argument)(Seems like "GDP = Consumption + Savings/Investment" by definition, so any unconsumed surplus is called "savings")</li>
<li>In summary, the only time it makes sense for a country to suppress wages (i.e. household income, which will mostly go towards consumption) is when it has high unemployment. In that case, increased investment compared to consumption will promote productive investment (<i>especially towards export</i>), and hence increase employment. After reaching high employment, continuing to suppress household income is effectively forcing unemployment in countries with policies less oriented towards thrift.</li>
<li>Financial repression through low interest rates might effectively be similar to devaluing the currency, because it shifts resources from households (consumption) to businesses (investment).</li>
</ul>

<div class="outline-2">
<h2 id="on-production-surpluses-and-income-inequality-appendix"><span class="section-number-2">1</span> On production surpluses and income inequality (appendix)</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Age of mass production &amp; mass consumption. Lacking capital for mass consumption, non-savers reduce consumption, so there's no return for savers investing capital to boost production &#x2013; unless consumers take on debt. So, <i>rising income inequality forces up the savings rate</i> since rich people can't/don't consume proportional to wealth (or redistribute for others to consume). If credit cannot surge enough, another consequence is rising unemployment (decreased production to match decreased demand) (This is what triggered New Deal policy making, as a response to Gilded Age inequality &#x2013; Marriner Eccles FRB Chairman 1932-1948).</li>
<li>If household income (as a fraction of GDP) shrinks, then households retain (and therefore consume) a smaller fraction of their productivity.</li>
<li>Pettis argues that different policies in Germany &amp; China which transfer money from households (suppress consumption) to producers (boost production) have similar effects.
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>In Germany, agreement circa ~2000 to restrain wage growth lower than productivity. German euro is "undervalued" in relation to Spain, Italy, France having "overvalued" euro.</li>
<li>In China, caused by a combination of large (rural) unemployment rate (and export-focused policies?). Undervalued yuan since 1994, and artificially low interest rates.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>If there are available avenues for productive investment (i.e. capital is the limiting factor determining growth i.e. "capital-ism"), inequality is a good eay of financing them &#x2013; since the rich will likely invest marginal gains, compared to the poor who will likely consume marginal gains. (Many developing countries suffer because of insufficient savings to bootstrap productive investments, simultaneously creating jobs).</li>
<li>Productivity improvements could result in increasing incomes or inequality (empirical analysis: Piketty's r-vs-g). When productivity improvements are sufficiently high (the target of juicy investment opportunities i.e. low-hanging fruit), household quality-of-life increases even when inequality does (can now consume more per unit income, so okay if incomes don't grow as much, esp. as a fraction of GDP), and the increased inequality is used to sponsor the next round of productivity improvements. This is the crux of the "trickle down" theory (where capitalists are mythologized as "job creators" leading progress; the phase the US "elite" believe themselves to be in).</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="outline-3">
<h3 id="what-happens-when-savings-rise-due-to-increasing-income-inequality"><span class="section-number-3">1.1</span> What happens when savings rise (due to increasing income inequality)?</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-1">
<p>
As an immediate consequence, productive investment must rise with savings, or it can be siphoned off into wasteful investment (excess inventory, or other useless endeavors).
</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>But (as Eccles pointed out) since the purpose of investment today is (to profit off) increased consumption tomorrow, productive investment will only happen if inequality were not permanent (and about to reverse). So, unlikely to get increase in productive investment.</li>
<li>Over short time periods, increasing inequality can be "buffered" by increasing inventory &#x2013; but likely people will not stupidly continue that over long periods.</li>
<li>Too much capital, and not enough investing opportunities, so interest rates will naturally fall &#x2013; and suddenly cheap capital will likely lead to speculative asset bubbles! Example unproductive investments:
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Infrastructure: unused {lavish buildings, swanky airports, highways, hosting a mega sporting event, etc}. Pettis claims: Arizona housing tracts, Dublin apartments, Spanish airports, Chinese ghost cities, etc.</li>
<li>Financial assets: overvalued securities.</li>
<li>Investment in zero-sum games (eg: Softbank &#x2013; WeWork and Uber; What about SuperPACs &#x2013; too small in scale?)</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="outline-3">
<h3 id="can-savings-increase-be-somehow-avoided-even-under-increasing-inequality"><span class="section-number-3">1.2</span> Can savings increase be somehow avoided, even under increasing inequality?</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-2">
<p>
Needs transfer of wealth from the rich to the poor. (eg: redistributive taxation to fuel consumption)
</p>
<ol class="org-ol">
<li>Wealthy households "consume" proportionally to income. Generically unlikely to happen, but one set of possibilities eg: by funding charity, research(alternatively seen as productive investment), etc (eg: Gilded age; Bill Gates). Also, politically unsustainable in a democracy.</li>
<li>Lower savings from poorer people to offset increased savings from wealthy people. eg: debt-fueled consumption (eg: student, home, credit-card loans; health-care funding?) but this is only possible whe there is an asset bubble (borrow against assets with increasing value, eg: houses, college degrees, etc.)
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Note: An (eventual) debt jubilee is akin to redistributive taxation, except morally unfair in punishing poor savers who held off unwise consumption (hence politicallly untenable, unless done "uniformly" eg: universal college education)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Increasing unemployment, so that you have a segment of population whose income drops to zero but consumption cannot, so they contribute negative to savings (either dip into their own savings, or borrow from others savings, or welfare from govt., or crime, etc.). This also reduces GDP, thereby reducing savings (since basic consumption will remain constant)</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<div class="outline-3">
<h3 id="universal-thrift-and-the-tragedy-of-the-commons"><span class="section-number-3">1.3</span> Universal thrift, and the tragedy of the commons</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-3">
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Bernard Mandeville's <i>Fable of the bees</i> was considered "un-christian" for stating that spending by the rich was good for the poor, and everyone becoming thrifty would be a disaster! (Interesting relation to Max Weber's Protestant ethic and the spirit of capitalism)</li>
<li>John Hobson, Confessions of an economic heretic (~1930s)</li>
<li>Thrift is great at an individual level; why not at the universal level?
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Thrift is either productive investment, or optionality by deferring consumption. If nobody is doing enough consumption today, the cycle breaks and economic flywheel decelerates. If everyone held on to money for optionality, no-one would be doing any value-generating activity. Yet another tragedy of the commons! (let others spend today, and I shall spend tomorrow when I might get more bang for the my buck, compared to today!)</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="outline-3">
<h3 id="applying-these-ideas-to-what-we-observe-in-the-world"><span class="section-number-3">1.4</span> Applying these ideas to what we observe in the world</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-4">
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Summary table of possible equilibrating responses to increased savings from income inequality.
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Of the six options, only "sustainable"<sup><a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="#fn.1">1</a></sup> ones are to put savings towards productive investments, or unemployment (or welfare &#x2013; either by the rich, or through the government with VERY HIGH marginal tax rates, which is one of the sub-cases of "linear consumption").</li>
<li>In the current political climate (welfare unlikely), if productive investments don't absorb savings, the only macroeconomic solution is unemployment.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>In the intermediate term, unsustainable possibilities include debt-fueled consumption, but that will likely increase debt beyond serviceable levels, so unlikely to continue.
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Examples galore in the US</li>
<li>Credit-financed consumption in Southern Europe, Housing bubbles around the (China, Canada, India?).</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Historically, unemployment starts in regions with fastest increase in debt (eg: US), but soon direct/indirect interventions in trade shift this to regions with high savings (eg: China, Germany)<sup><a id="fnr.2" class="footref" href="#fn.2">2</a></sup>.
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Regions with surpluses are dependent on high-demand regions to siphon off the savings &amp; excess production, otherwise their own supply and demand cannot balance, and all their hitherto productive investments will turn unproductive (unless they can raise their consumption drastically). This is the position China &amp; Germany are in.</li>
<li>Nicely worked out example of Germany-Spain system. (Presumably could equally well have been Greece instead of Spain. Also, I wonder whether this explains the impetus for the Catalonian separatist movement)</li>
<li>Trade war is how regions negotiate/assign global unemployment; so expect trade tensions to be increasingly focal over the next several years.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>"Austerity economics" is completely wrong, because it presumes that universal thrift is a positive thing; in reality, you're always playing whack-a-mole to try and bury the excess savings in a zero-sum game. <i>The solution is not for low-savings countries to cut back on consumption, but for high-savings countries to increase consumption (lest they be forced into unemployment!)</i></li>
<li>At the global level, there are only three sustainable options:
<ol class="org-ol">
<li>Increase in consumption by saving groups (Something China is trying to do<sup><a id="fnr.3" class="footref" href="#fn.3">3</a></sup>, and Germany has tepid steps towards)</li>
<li>Direct savings into productive investment instead of producing inventory for export (and trying to export away savings)
Private sector reluctance (hard to capture value), so likely government funded (eg: China research funding, CERN Higgs factory, Infrastructure projects towards productivity, etc.)</li>
<li>High unemployment in savings heavy region.</li>
<li>The above changes will likely be slow, so (as a stop gap) need countries with productive investment opportunities to keep demand high while the structural distortions are worked out.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>The first country to introduce downward wealth re-distribution will likely export away the employment and growth that result from a surge in consumption (effectively donating away the savings). Reduced global trade will likely provide impetus for local downward redistribution, but not until then.</li>
<li>Increasing debt-fueled consumption in the US, or export-oriented investments in China are likely to worsen the underlying structural imbalances.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="outline-3">
<h3 id="in-summary"><span class="section-number-3">1.5</span> In summary</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-5">
<blockquote>
<p>
<i>"It is utterly impossible, as this country has demonstrated again and again, for the rich to save as much as they have been trying to save, and save anything that is worth saving. They can save idle factories and useless railroad coaches; they can save empty office buildings and closed banks; they can save paper evidences of foreign loans; but as a class they cannot save anything that is worth saving, above and beyond the amount that is made profitable by the increase of consumer buying. It is for the interests of the well-to-do &#x2013; to protect them from the results of their own folly &#x2013; that we should take from them a sufficient amount of their surplus to enable consumers to consume and business to operate at a profit. This is not “soaking the rich”; it is saving the rich. Incidentally, it is the only way to assure them the serenity and security which they do not have at the present moment."</i>  (Marriner Eccles testimony to the US Congress, 1933)
</p>
</blockquote>
</div>
</div>
<div class="outline-3">
<h3 id="my-comments"><span class="section-number-3">1.6</span> My comments</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-6">
<ul class="org-ul">
<li><i>FRB further injecting "liquidity" into capital markets is akin to pouring fuel on the fire, because it's all meant to go towards investment!</i> Also, perversely, generating debt to fuel investment is effectively claiming that inequality is <i>"not high enough"</i> to produce the necessary investment, for the given consumption level!</li>
<li>Note: <b>The same likely applies even if the inequality is driven by technology/automation, and in fact explains the imperial dynamics of the industrial revolution quite well!</b></li>
<li>PS: Apart from inequality, population dynamics also contribute to the dynamics of savings. Young and old people weigh heavily on the consumption, while middle-aged people weigh heavily on savings&#x2026; either for retirement, or to fuel consumption of the other two groups under their umbrella. An excess of savings-age population (unwilling to retire) will also likely cause complications.</li>
<li>Unemployment in high-savings regions is reminiscent of the Maxwell construction for phase mixtures, stabilizing otherwise metastable states. (Employment being the order parameter; savings among employed must match consumption among unemployed)</li>
<li>Alternate solution to "unemployment" &#x2013; instead of reducing the number of employed people, reduce the per-capita working hours.</li>
<li>Basically, the rest of the world refuses to act as the "bank" for the thrifty, allowing them to run up large and sustained surpluses, because that is a hard promise to keep.</li>
<li>The savings glut from US inequality combined with the savings glut from China has been a double whammy on the Rust Belt[fn::which is exactly where unemployment hit first! Only, the Republicans &amp; progressive Democrats disagree on which of the two sources of savings glut to squeeze, while the moderate Democrats are stuck) (and rural US more broadly).</li>
<li>Done well, healthcare welfare might be one form of wealth redistribution which is very difficult to export away to China (largely a service industry, and most value of drugs captured in the US). Likewise education, since American students don't go abroad for college. (<i>I don't mean loans, unless they're loans that are meant to be forgiven</i>). This would reduce (structural) inequality, by pipint (rich people) savings towards (poor people) consumption; any improvement in productive capacity from improved health or capabilities is a bonus.</li>
<li>Applications to India? Sainath has mentioned that since the opening up of India's economy, India has had <b>massive</b> inequality growth. How does that affect unemployment, and trade deficits? Also, the propensity to buy gold contributes to the deficitr</li>
<li>Applications to intra-US politics &#x2013; rural(central)-vs-urban(bicoastal)?</li>
<li>Why do religions forbid lending with interest?</li>
<li>We saw a use of this perspective to analyze the industrial revolution and imperialism. What about analyzing automation?</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="footnotes">
<h2 class="footnotes">Footnotes: </h2>
<div id="text-footnotes">

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="#fnr.1">1</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">nature has a way of <i>forcing</i> ecosystems to become sustainable</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.2" class="footnum" href="#fnr.2">2</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">Written in 2013, this seems incredibly prescient about the Trump phenomenon</p></div></div>

<div class="footdef"><sup><a id="fn.3" class="footnum" href="#fnr.3">3</a></sup> <div class="footpara"><p class="footpara">Third Plenum reform proposals</p></div></div>


</div>
</div>]]></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on &#34;A fine balance&#34; by Rohinton Mistry</title>
      <link>http://sivark.me/blog/thoughts-on-a-fine-balance-by-rohinton-mistry.html</link>
      <author>author@mail.com (Blog Author)</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://sivark.me/blog/thoughts-on-a-fine-balance-by-rohinton-mistry.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>
The book was needed some effort to get through the first third or so (took me a week!), while Mistry sets up his four characters and brings them together. After that, it's simply un-put-downable and I read the remaining two-thirds in one sitting. When I finished, it was 7am in the morning and I'd been reading all night!
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
<i>Life is a comedy to those who think and tragedy to those who feel.</i>
</p>
</blockquote>


<p>
It's impossible not to feel overwhelmed by the absolutely heart-wrenching tale. I feel devastated and bitter. 1984 is the only other book which affected me like this. Wretched story but sublime writing&#x2026; it feels effortless and poignant at the same time. I typically read to seek escape, but this is <i>so</i> not the kind of book for that. I definitely wasn't prepared for this.
</p>

<p>
The book had some fine humour &#x2013; spontaneous and witty and made me really laugh. It shows how people in the direst situations are still capable of laughing genuinely. And smile and hope. And just when you think that the glimmer of hope will lead to sunrise, Mistry pulls out the rug from under your feet and leaves you with a cold and treacherous dawn followed by sunshine as normal, which seems particularly cruel since it does little to shine light on the protagonist's lives, almost as if it were a matter-of-fact occurrence and their suffering was nobody's concern.
</p>

<p>
The author has produced something so stunning that I feel thoroughly inadequate to judge it. The question that haunts me is: what do I get out of this book? What to make of it? It is such a awe-stricking experience that I can't just let it be and move on.
</p>

<p>
It feels like a tragedy without any moral or lesson to learn. Almost every character in the book is a good and sincere person (limited by a perspective based on their circumstances) but fickle fate wrings them through misery for no obvious reason &#x2013; to the extent that their fight almost seems futile. It conveys the hopelessness and powerlessness felt by the protagonists &#x2013; which denies you any possible sense of catharsis. Everything seems bleak, with no hope for redemption.
</p>

<p>
If I had to manufacture some meaning, I'd say that it gives me a hint of how incredibly privileged a life I lead, compared to a large number of people. An author doesn't always need to have an upshot for a book. It could be an honest <i>description</i> leaving the readers to make their own observations.
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
<i>"You fellows are amazing&#x2026; Everything happens to you only. Each time you come here, you have a new adventure story to entertain us"</i>
</p>
</blockquote>


<p>
Because of all the challenges the protagonists faced, they come away with the most stories. They can at least feel good that they did not live out their drudgery silently but like the spider, they were constantly trying to climb out of the well even if they kept slipping and sliding on the slime. Their lives and struggles have a certain depth and dignity. Maybe that's the only honest measure of a life <i>"well-lived"</i>.
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
<i>"You see, you cannot draw lines and compartments, and refuse to budge beyond them. Sometimes you have to use your failures as stepping-stones to success. You have to maintain a fine balance between hope and despair."</i>
</p>
</blockquote>
]]></description>
    </item>
    

  </channel>
</rss>
